Guide to the Armistead Burt Papers, 1759-1933 RL.10107
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Armistead Burt papers
1759-1933
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Burt, A. (Armistead)
RL.10107
3.6 Linear Feet 9 boxes; 5,675 items
Armistead Burt (1802-1883) was a planter, lawyer, and U.S. Representative from Abbeville, S.C. Collection contains political and legal correspondence of Armistead Burt (1802-1883), South Carolina planter and member of U.S. Congress. The political correspondence deals largely with the policies of John C. Calhoun and the question of secession. After 1860 the material relates chiefly to Burt's law practice, especially to the management of estates of Confederate soldiers, and the Calhoun estate. Other matters referred to include the political corruption and economic conditions in postwar South Carolina. Among the correspondents are Armistead Burt, Pierce M. Butler, Henry Toole Clark, Thomas Green Clemson, T. L. Deveaux, James H. Hammond, A. P. Hayne, Reverdy Johnson, Hugh S. Legare, Augustus B. Longstreet, W. N. Meriwether, James L. Petigru, Francis W. Pickens, Robert Barnwell Rhett, Richard Rush, Waddy Thompson, and Louis T. Wigfall.
Collection Overview
Collection includes the political and legal correspondence of Armistead Burt (1802-1883), South Carolina planter and member of U.S. Congress.
The political correspondence deals largely with the policies of John C. Calhoun and the question of secession. After 1860 the material relates chiefly to Burt's law practice, especially to the management of estates of Confederate soldiers, and the Calhoun estate. Other matters referred to include the political corruption and economic conditions in postwar South Carolina. Among the correspondents are Armistead Burt, Pierce M. Butler, Henry Toole Clark, Thomas Green Clemson, T. L. Deveaux, James H. Hammond, A. P. Hayne, Reverdy Johnson, Hugh S. Legare, Augustus B. Longstreet, W. N. Meriwether, James L. Petigru, Francis W. Pickens, Robert Barnwell Rhett, Richard Rush, Waddy Thompson, and Louis T. Wigfall.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Armistead Burt (1802-1883) was a planter, lawyer, and U.S. Representative from Abbeville, S.C.
Provenance
The Armistead Burt Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1934 and 1940.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into the following series: Correspondence, Legal Papers, Financial Papers, Other Writings
Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877) -- South Carolina; South Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Secession; Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850
- Correspondence Series, 1825-1896 and undated; 24 folders
  Scope and Contents
  Series includes political and legal correspondence mostly related to John C. Calhoun and the secession question. Later correspondence deals with Burt's law practice. Correspondents include: Pierce M. Butler, Henry Toole Clark, Thomas Green Clemson, T. L. Deveaux, James H. Hammond, A. P. Hayne, Reverdy Johnson, Hugh S. Legaré, Augustus B. Longstreet, W. N. Meriwether, james L. Petigru, Francis W. Pickens, Robert Barnwell Rhett, Richard Rush, Waddy Thompson, and Louis T. Wigfall.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically
  - Correspondence, 1825-1847; 4 folders (Box 1)
    Black-and-white photographs
  - Correspondence, 1848-1849 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1850 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1851-1852 June (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1852 July-1858 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1859-1862 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1863-1864 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1865-1866 June (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1866-1872; 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1873-1876; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1877-1896; undated; 5 folders (Box 5)
- Legal Papers Series, 1759-1874 and undated; 10 folders
  Series includes legal papers, mostly related to Burt's law practice, especially the management of estates of Confederate soldiers, and the Calhoun estate.
  - Legal papers, 1759-1870; 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Legal papers, 1871-1874; undated; 4 folders (Box 7)
- Financial Papers Series, 1823-1875 and undated; 10 folders
  Financial papers chiefly relate to the management of estates of Confederate soldiers and the Calhoun estate.
  - Financial papers, 1823-1859; 6 folders (Box 8)
  - Financial papers, 1860-1875; undated; 4 folders (Box 9)
- Other Writings Series, 1794-1933 and undated; 1 folder
  - Other writings, 1794-1933; undated; 1 folder